Chelsie S. Johnston

Belleville, IL, USA | (312) 402-8294 | chelsiesjohnston@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/chelsiesjohnston | https://chelsie.dev

SUMMARY

Seasoned "started-in-childhood" developer returning to the field with over a decade of professional experience crafting reliable and visually polished Drupal sites at scale; body of work spans a diverse range of nonprofits, universities, international brands, and government agencies; effective in stakeholder negotiation and requirements gathering; highly communicative remote and in-person collaborator with an enthusiasm for process iteration and team development; creative, passionate autodidact with an eagerness to integrate leadership into an already deep front end engineering skill set, as well as expand skills lower down the stack.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Senior Front End Developer, Last Call Media

Remote — Feb 2019 - Aug 2022

Bridged the gap between design and engineering in a fully distributed agency. Acted as a liaison to the design team in an advisory role alongside coding robust, performant experiences and contributing PR reviews as a developer.

Notable projects:

- **New England Foundation for the Arts** Built a decoupled React front end to consume a Drupal-based API for the Creativeground.org website, supporting over 11,000 artists and patrons in fostering creative partnerships
- **Blackboard.com** Crafted a WCAG 2.1 compliant component library and theme for the education brand's Drupal site using SCSS and JavaScript, leading to a lower homepage bounce rate and an increase in signups
- Instant Brands (formerly Corelle Brands) Enhanced Drupal themes using SCSS and JS to accommodate on-the-fly addition of new brands, ensuring cohesive UX during a pivotal sales period
- Mannequin.io Prior maintainer for a directly consumable, open-source component library tool
- Key technologies: JavaScript ES6, TypeScript, React, CSS-in-JS, Twig, HTML5, CSS3, SCSS, PHP, Jest, Cypress, BackstopJS, Git, Docker, CircleCI, Mannequin

Software Engineer II, American Medical Association

Chicago, IL — Aug 2016 - Jul 2018

Built and maintained public and member-facing Drupal websites with up-to-the-minute resources for doctors and medical professionals. Collaborated closely with UX designers and contributed code and PR reviews as part of a cross-functional project team.

Notable projects:

- Front End/Style Guide Project leadership Led a front-end team in conceptualizing, developing, and
 maintaining an integrated component library using PatternLab, providing cohesive branding across the AMA's
 diverse web properties; initialized clean front end code standards with a focus on accessibility for end users
- Key technologies: JavaScript ES6, PatternLab, HTML5, CSS3, SCSS, PHP, BackstopJS, Vagrant, Travis, Git

Front End Developer, The University of Chicago

 $\label{lem:chicago} \begin{tabular}{l} Chicago, IL-May 2013-Aug 2016 (Front End Developer, UChicago Web Services dept.) \\ Chicago, IL-Sep 2012-May 2013 (Project Delivery Contractor, UChicago Project Management Office) \\ \end{tabular}$

Dual focus as a designer; reshaped departmental processes while supporting the University's outreach and recruitment mission through delivery of Drupal and ExpressionEngine websites for degree programs and academic research

organizations. Forged empathetic relationships with stakeholders via educational hands-on design sessions, streamlining time to delivery.

Notable projects:

- Client-facing Process Innovation Spearheaded the overhaul of the University's in-house web design process by implementing atomic design principles and transitioning from waterfall to agile project management methodologies, resulting in cost savings and stronger client relationships
- **UChicago News** Designed and developed the UChicago News website (D7 to D8 migration and full redesign) using SCSS, JS, and PHP, empowering editors with captivating storytelling capabilities while maintaining a structured content architecture
- **UChicago Sites** Maintained a Drupal template site service that provided over 300 University organizations with design and content flexibility while ensuring alignment with the University brand
- Key technologies: JavaScript, jQuery, HTML5, CSS3, SCSS, PHP, BackstopJS, Git

IT Assistant, Spurlock Museum, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

Urbana, IL — Sep 2009 - Aug 2011

Notable projects:

- **Web and kiosk development** Conceptualized and built digital experiences for web and in-person exhibit kiosks using HTML, CSS, Javascript, and Adobe Creative Suite, allowing museum patrons to deeply engage with historical artifacts from across the world
- **Accessibility compliance** Tested and documented the patron-facing website's compliance with emerging web accessibility (A11y) standards, making the Museum's collections and events more inclusive

LEADERSHIP AND SPEAKING

Volunteer Technical Lead, Women Who Code - St. Louis, MO

 $St. Louis, MO-Nov\ 2023$ - present

Help organize and host online and in-person networking events, empowering a diverse population of
underserved technical professionals to find community, seek employment, and improve technical skills; mentor
junior developers

Presenter: NERD Summit 2020; Midwest Area Drupal Camp 2016

EDUCATION

University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

Champaign, IL - May 2012

BA Communication, concentration in Sociocultural and Linguistic Anthropology

CONTINUING EDUCATION AND SUPPLEMENTAL SKILLS

- Currently learning Java
- Adept at exploring ambiguous product ideas and architecting them into clearly scoped, organized requirements that meet business goals; adept at engaging with stakeholders to identify potential risks and justify trade-offs
- Committed to supporting Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion in tech